Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov.
Today's דף Daf is מ"ב Mem-Beit officially, but we are wrapping up,
so we're at the bottom of מ"א... Mem-Aleph... we're on the top
of מ"א Mem-Aleph עמוד ב. Amud-Beit. And we are dealing with the
debate of... or it's at the bottom of מ"ב עמוד א... mem-bet
amud aleph. מ"א Mem-Aleph עמוד א. Amud-Aleph... We're dealing with the debate
of whether half קנס Kanas by a goring ox... no top of
מ"א Mem-Aleph עמוד ב. Amud-Beit. Half half payment of a goring ox
is considered קנס Kanas or ממון. Mamon. The biggest difference is if
somebody admits it do they have to pay or not. The משנה
Mishnah says only if you pay more than the normal damages can
we assume it's קנס Kanas else it might be partial payment. But
nevertheless, we see that there's a debate of אמוראים Amoraim about this
in terms of whether we can assume that oxen are normally considered
to be watched and guarded like naturally without doing anything and therefore
when it goes out and gores and it's an and it's a
תם, Tam, it's actually falls shy of being actual negligence and therefore
would be a קנס, Kanas, or is it actually just over the
line of being negligent and it would be ממון Mamon but because
it's just barely, it's half it's half payment. So now the גמרא
Gemara picks up on the top of מ"א Mem-Aleph עמוד ב Amud-Beit
and let's just try to quickly wrap this up. תא שמע Ta
Shma come and hear. המזיק שורו של פלוני או שורו של פלוני
הרי זה משלם על פי עצמו.
Ha-mazik shoro shel ploni o shoro shel ploni
harey zeh meshaleim al pi atzmo.
So if somebody says my ox gored a person... and as we
discussed, that would be a payment of the actual כופר, Kofer, the
monetary value of the person himself, which is being assumed here as
a type of תשלומים, Tashlumim, we're not going to focus on that.
Or his person's ox, then he pays by his own admission. מאי
לאו בתם Mai lav betam are we not talking about a non-habituated
ox and therefore he's paying by his own admission, it shows that
it's ממון? Mamon? And the גמרא Gemara says לא במועד, Lo bemuad,
no, we're talking about habituated. The גמרא Gemara says אבל בתם מאי?
Aval betam mai? So what would you say therefore if it was
a case of a תם? Tam? אינו משלם על פי עצמו Eino
meshaleim al pi atzmo you would say he would not pay based
on his own admission because then you would claim it would be
a קנס. Kanas. אדתני סיפא Ad'tani seifa so if the end of
the ברייתא Braita says עבדו של פלוני אינו משלם על פי עצמו
Avdo shel Ploni eino meshaleim al pi atzmo that when you admit
to your ox goring somebody's slave you don't pay by your own
admission because a slave is thirty shekels a fixed amount, it's a
קנס, Kanas, right? So the ברייתא Braita there is contrasting the goring
a free person where it's תשלומים Tashlumim as opposed to a slave
where it's קנס. Kanas. So why did it have to jump to
a slave case? נפלוג וניתני בדידיה Niflog u-nitni bedidih why don't you
make a distinction within the case itself? במה דברים אמורים Bamah devarim
amurim when is it when you don't pay by your own admission?
I mean that you do pay by your own admission when it's
habituated. אבל תם אינו משלם על פי עצמו Aval tam eino meshaleim
al pi atzmo but if it's an unhabituated, if it's a תם,
Tam, you don't pay on your own admission even if it's a
case of goring another ox or goring a free person, right? The
fact that you had to run to the case of slave seems
to indicate that in a normal case you would always pay even
if it was a case of a תם. Tam. So the גמרא
Gemara says so that seems to indicate that even a תם Tam
is considered תשלומים. Tashlumim. כולה במועד קאמרי Kulah bemuad kamari
no, that doesn't prove anything. Maybe we don't want to be talking
about a תם. Tam. Maybe we want to be talking about a
habituated ox and say even within a habituated ox there's differences. Goring
an ox and goring a free person is תשלומים, Tashlumim, goring a
slave is a קנס. Kanas. But you know what, it's true, there's
other cases like an unhabituated ox, a תם, Tam, that also would
be a קנס. Kanas. So the fact that we jumped to the
case of slave doesn't show anything about whether we feel whether תם
Tam itself is תשלומים Tashlumim or not. Okay, תא שמע Ta Shma
come and hear going to our משנה. Mishnah. זה הכלל Zeh haklal
this is the rule. כל המשלם יותר על מה שהזיק אינו משלם
על פי עצמו. Kol hameshaleim yoter al mah she-hizik eino meshaleim al
pi atzmo. Anytime you pay more than damages you don't pay based
on your own admission, that's clearly a קנס Kanas a fine because
it's exceeding the damages or it's thirty of an עבד Eved which
at times could exceed the damages shows that it's a fine. So
the גמרא Gemara says אינו משלם על פי עצמו. Eino meshaleim al
pi atzmo. הפחות ממה שהזיק Hapochot mimah she-hizik
if you pay less than damages than full damages משלם על פי
עצמו meshaleim al pi atzmo presumably you would pay based on your
own admission. If you're always paying half, then we shouldn't consider that
a fine, we should consider that partial payment.
And therefore you pay based on your own admission.
Doesn't that seem to be indicated in our משנה? Mishnah? גמרא Gemara
says no.
לא תימא הפחות ממה
שהזיק
Lo teima
hapochot mimah she-hizik don't say less than the full amount would be
תשלומים. Tashlumim. אלא אימא הכמה שהזיק משלם על פי עצמו. Ela eima
hakama she-hizik meshaleim al pi atzmo.
When it's exactly the full amount, that's when it's תשלומים. Tashlumim. But
anything more is קנס Kanas and maybe anything less is also קנס.
Kanas. But when it's exactly the same amount as damages, that's when
it's תשלומים. Tashlumim. So the גמרא Gemara says... אלא אימא הכמה שהזיק
משלם על פי עצמו. Ela eima hakama she-hizik meshaleim al pi atzmo.
So the גמרא Gemara says אבל פחות מאי? Aval pochot mai?
So one minute, the גמרא Gemara is saying, you're saying that according
to the משנה, Mishnah, not only is more קנס Kanas but even
less is קנס. Kanas. So אבל פחות מאי? Aval pochot mai? אינו
משלם על פי עצמו? Eino meshaleim al pi atzmo? So if it's
less you also don't pay? ליתני זה הכלל כל שאינו משלם כמה
שהזיק אינו משלם על פי עצמו. Liteni zeh haklal kol she-eino meshaleim
kemah she-hizik eino meshaleim al pi atzmo.
Then the משנה Mishnah should have been more precise. The משנה Mishnah
should have said whenever you don't pay exactly according to damages then
you don't
pay. So everybody get it? The משנה Mishnah says if you pay
more than full damages or potentially more, like the thirty of an
עבד, eved, it's a קנס. knas. So the strong implication is less
is not a קנס, knas, less is partial payment. And if you
wanted to say the משנה Mishnah really meant whether more or less,
then say that. Say if it's exactly the damages then it's תשלומין
tashlumin and anything more and anything less is a קנס. knas. It
doesn't say that. It says if it's more it's a קנס, knas,
which means less is not a קנס. knas. So the גמרא Gemara
says תיובתא, tyufta, you know what, you're right. That is a contradiction
to the idea of the one that says that it's a קנס.
knas. The משנה Mishnah very strongly suggests that unless it's more than
damages, it's going to be a קנס. knas. Anything less will also
be considered תשלומין. tashlumin. So the גמרא Gemara says so you're right.
That contradicts the idea that half payment is a קנס, knas, seems
to very explicitly indicate that half payment is תשלומין. tashlumin. So the
גמרא Gemara says, and but just to make things fun, והלכתא, vehilchasa,
but the ruling is פלגא ניזקא קנסא, palga nizka knasa, that half
of the damages is a קנס. knas. So the משנה Mishnah makes
it almost explicit that it's תשלומין tashlumin and we rule that it's
a קנס. knas. So the גמרא Gemara says תיובתא והלכתא? tyufta vehilchasa?
What, you contradict it and then you rule that way? I says
אין, in, yes. טעמא מאי איתותב? taama mai itosav?
Why was the position of half damages as a קנס knas contradicted?
משום דלא קתני כמו שהזיק, mishum delo ktani k'moshehizik, because it didn't
say תשלומין tashlumin is exactly the same amount. It said, you know,
it said anything more, not anything different than the exact. So that
indicated that something less would be תשלומין. tashlumin. Okay, that was your
contradiction. I'll give you a reason why it didn't say that. So
the גמרא Gemara says לא פסיקא ליה, lo psika leh, because it
was not absolute, it was not categorical that the real rule is
that less is also a קנס. knas. But there's one exception to
the rule so we couldn't exactly say it. What was the exception
to the rule? כיון דאיכא חצי נזק צרורות דהלכתא גמירי לה, keivan
ika chatzi nezek tzoros dehilchasa gemiri lah, that half damages which is
paid by pebbles.
What does that mean? It means that if an ox is walking
and tramples on vessels as it's walking, that's the נזק nezek of
רגל, regel, it pays full damages. If it's walking and it kicks
up stones and the stones breaks things, then it pays half damages.
And that's right. And that is a הלכה למשה מסיני. halachah l'Moshe
mi'Sinai. And there we are, there's no question that that's considered רגל
regel and that actually it is, well first I mean רגל, regel,
it's a form of תשלומי רגל, tashlumei regel, and that it pays
half and that it's תשלומין. tashlumin. And that therefore the half damages
there is תשלומין. tashlumin. So the גמרא Gemara says really our משנה
Mishnah did not say that if it's not exact it's a קנס
knas because there is a case that's not exact that's less that's
ממון, mamon, which is this case of צרורות. tzoros. But the real
rule is bracketing the exception of צרורות, tzoros, anything that's not exactly
the תשלומין, tashlumin, whether it's more or whether it's less, is going
to be a קנס. knas. And half payment of a תם, tam,
of a goring ox, is actually going to be a קנס. knas.
Okay? דהלכתא גמירי דממונא הוא משום הכי לא קתני. dehilchasa gemiri de'mamona
hu mishum hachi lo ktani. Okay, so that is the גמרא's Gemara
conclusion. The was pretty much the only two that it's always exact,
it's always less. Otherwise it's more or thirty of an עבד eved
which sometimes is more sometimes is less.
Even if the thrust was that it was ממון? mamon? I do
understand. And despite that we ruled it was a קנס.
knas. Yeah, right, so that is correct. Meaning all of the evidence
seems to point to the idea that פלגא ניזקא palga nizka that
half damages is ממון, mamon, right? All of the evidence we brought
yesterday and the wrap-up of the סוגיא sugya today. And nevertheless the
גמרא Gemara concludes that and logically if you're paying half of something,
the logic is is that that is partial payment, not that it's
you should be paying zero but it's a קנס. knas. The logic
is that it's partial payment, and that's what we say by the
צרורות tzoros case, by the pebbles being kicked by the walking animal.
Nevertheless we conclude that this is a קנס. knas. I don't know,
the גמרא Gemara had a tradition that this was the הלכה, halachah,
that this was a קנס. knas. And therefore maybe it's just decided
that, you know, that a תם tam logically there's no negligence so
it logically should be a קנס. knas. What negligence is it that
an ox would go out and gore? So therefore that's the גמרא's
Gemara conclusion. And even though the משנה Mishnah makes it sound that
in order to be a קנס knas it has to be beyond
damages, more than damages, right? But nevertheless it's saying no, there are
times when even it's less than damages it's also a קנס. knas.
Okay, sometimes yes, sometimes no. Half damages by a goring תם, tam,
that would be a קנס. knas. Half damages by the צרורות, tzoros,
that would be תשלומין, tashlumin, yes.
What's the conceptual relationship between על פי עצמו al pi atzmo and
תשלומין? tashlumin?
That anytime we consider to be תשלומין, tashlumin, ממון, mamon, then you
pay based on על פי עצמו. al pi atzmo. They go together.
Why do they go together?
Because you're always believed to obligate yourself in court to say that
you owe somebody money. The only point is is that when it's
קנס, knas, when it's seen as a monetary fine imposed by בית
דין, beis din, then the same way בית דין beis din won't
impose lashes on you based on your own admission, we need objective
testimony, they won't impose monetary, the same way they won't impose bodily
punishments on you based on your own admission, they won't impose monetary
punishments based on your own admission. Needs objective testimony, but admission to
a debt you can be, you know, is even על פי עצמו.
al pi atzmo. Yeah.
So, the גמרא Gemara just eventually got back to the משנה, Mishna,
which is the case we're in front of us. It dealt with
everything else until it got there, ignoring the most obvious proof. That
typical, that we did?
Well, I don't know, it's a good question. Maybe we waited for
it for last, maybe this סוגיא sugya was not originally on the
משנה, Mishna, because this סוגיא sugya might have been originally in בבא
קמא Bava Kamma and then just pasted on here to the משנה.
Mishna.
Okay. Isn't it always בית דין Beis Din is not פטור patur
דאורייתא? d'Oraisa?
No, no, no. קנס knas is imposed,
for example, the idea that you pay double in a case of
גניבה gneiva or four and five is in the תורה, Torah, but
the, but the same way lashes are in the תורה. Torah. But
if I go ahead, if I say, if I owe you a
hundred dollars, with or without בית דין, Beis Din, I pay you
up, that, that exists. And if I pay you up, I've, I've,
I've exempted myself from that debt, I've discharged that debt. If I
go ahead and I transgress a negative prohibition, it's not like objectively
I deserve lashes, and if I go ahead and impose self-imposed lashes,
now I've, now I've gotten out of my obligation. Right? The, the
idea that the transgression empowers בית דין Beis Din to therefore rule
that I am obligated and to impose those lashes. It doesn't exist
independent of the court. But the, but בית דין Beis Din is
directed by the תורה Torah to rule and impose lashes, and the
same would be by the קנס. knas. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara continues and it says the following: והשתא דאמרת פלגא ניזקא קנסא,
v'hashta d'amart palga nizka knasa,
now that you said that half damages is a קנס knas when
it's a case of a קרן keren of a goring ox, which
means normally a קרן keren is understood to be an animal that
intentionally damages. Okay. But now what we're going to do is we're
going to list cases where an animal does damage which is משונה,
meshuneh, unusual and unexpected, and something you wouldn't guard against. And there's
an interesting question whether what the גמרא Gemara is doing is it's
saying that anytime it's unusual that puts it in the category of
קרן, keren, because normally we assume קרן keren means an animal that's
willfully damaging. Okay, not, but, but here the גמרא's Gemara's going to
deal with the cases of משונה. meshuneh. So one way of understanding
is that it's categorizing it as קרן. keren. The other way is
no, but let's take a look at the cases. Okay. האי כלבא,
hai kalba, so if a certain dog דאכל אימרי d'achal imri that
eats lambs, ושונרא v'shunra or a cat דאכל תרנגולי d'achal tarnegoli that
eats chickens,
רברבי, ravrevi, if they're large lambs or chickens, משונה הוא, meshuneh hu,
then it's an unusual act. ולא מגבינן בבבל, v'lo magbinan b'Vavel, and
therefore it would be a קנס knas and would only be half
damages. And another application of קנס knas is not only that you
don't pay based on your own admission, but as we were talking
about before, it requires a court to impose it. And not only
any court, but the same way only a court that has, that
has סמיכה smicha going back to משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu is called
אלהים, Elohim, has that, has that like original סמיכה, smicha, since only
that type of a court can impose lashes, also you need that
type of a court to impose a monetary קנס. knas. And therefore
it cannot be done outside of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. It was
assumed that those courts are only empowered in Israel. They only have
סמיכה smicha is given in Israel, that type of סמיכה, smicha, and
those courts are empowered in Israel. So therefore you cannot collect things
that are קנס, knas, not only based on your own admission, you
can't collect them without the right court and you can't impose them
outside of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Now the question is why is
something משונה meshuneh considered to be קרן? keren? קרן keren is a
goring intentional animal. Here's an animal that's trying to eat a chicken
or trying to eat a lamb. What makes it a קרן? keren?
It should be like a שן, shein, an animal that does something
as an act of eating is in a different category. So basically
there's a lot of fun discussion in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, there
are two approaches. One approach is that this is the חידוש, chiddush,
since it's not a normal type of eating it gets categorized as
קרן keren in the same category as intentional damage. The other approach
is no, maybe it is a שן, shein, but the same way
by a goring animal when it gores in a way that you
should not, you could not have protected against, that you were not
negligent for, like the first few times you only pay half damages.
So maybe when an animal does a type of an eating that
you couldn't have protected against, an eating that was totally unexpected and
that was a תם tam for, maybe also you only pay half
damages and it's also a type of a קנס. knas. And then
there becomes this interesting idea of half damages not only for קרן,
keren, but even for something like שן shein and רגל. regel. So
that's an interesting discussion in בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. But for us
what we have to know is that if it's this unusual type
of thing, it similarly would be half damages and similarly would be
a קנס. knas. ולא מגבינן בבבל. v'lo magbinan b'Vavel. אבל זוטרי, aval
zutrei, if it eats small animals, then אורחיה הוא, orchei hu, that's
normal, ומגבינן u'magbinan and we collect. ואי תפס לא מפקינן מיניה, v'ee
tafas lo mafkinan minei, and even if we won't as a court
rule that the guy has to pay, if the damagee grabs money
equivalent to the, to the, to the injury or to half the
cost of the injury from the damager, then we will not force
him to give the, to give the property back. Of course the
funny thing is then we'll have to have a court case to
decide how much the damages were and whether he's entitled to keep
as much as he grabbed. Anyway, ואי אמר אקבעו לי זימנא לארץ
ישראל, v'ee amar akvu li zimna l'Eretz Yisrael, and if he says
though, if the damagee says to the, says to our בית דין,
Beis Din, make let, you know, I want to set up a
court case in Israel and have the damager come to me to
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael so... I can collect my due, מכבינן ליה
machbinan lei then we do make a make an appointment for him
in a בית דין Beis Din in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael that
the damagee can take the damager to. ואי לא אזיל ve'ee lo
azil and if the damager won't go, משמטינן ליה, meshamtinan lei, we
put him in חרם cherem in order until he goes so therefore
the damagee is not completely without recourse. בין כך ובין כך bein
kach u'vein kach and whether or not he sets up a time
the damagee to go to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, either way משמטינן
ליה meshamtinan lei we will put the damager in חרם cherem until
he takes care of his dangerous animal. דאמרינן ליה סלק היזקך, de'amrinan
lei salek hezekach, we say remove your dangerous animal.
But that's not necessarily because of Rabbi Natan.
Well that's an interesting point. You're right. You could have said it's
a תם tam and maybe we would see it as a like
as an exception, as a freak incident. But it's interesting, we don't.
And that's an excellent point. דתניא detanya Rabbi Natan אומר, omer, Rabbi
Natan says, מנין שלא יגדל אדם כלב רע בתוך ביתו, minayin shelo
yigadel adam kelev ra betoch beito, how do you know a person
shouldn't raise a mad dog in his house? ולא יעמיד סולם רעוע
בתוך ביתו v'lo ya'amid sulam ra'ua betoch beito or have a shaky
ladder, שנאמר, shene'emar, ולא תשים דמים בביתך. v'lo tasim damim b'veitecha. So
Michael makes a good point, like do we always do this or
only if the animal is starting to become more habitual or we
have concerns that even if it's the first time it won't be
the last time. Anyway, not clear. הדרן לך אלו נערות. hadran lach
elu naarot. So that was wrapping up from yesterday, a very nice
sort of digression into בבא קמא Bava Kamma land about when do
we consider something to be ממון mamon and קנס, knas, whether when
it gets to be the fifty shekel is always קנס knas because
that's seen as going beyond any damages and it's a fixed amount.
But something that is not a fixed amount that is half damages,
that was an interesting discussion. We would naturally consider that to be
partial תשלומין. tashlumim. The גמרא Gemara said at least in some cases
like by the goring animal that would be a קנס. knas. But
a fixed amount and something that could be more than damages is
always going to be קנס knas with two הלכות halachot so far,
one is you don't pay based on your own admission and the
other is as we've seen that you need a court to impose
it and only a court with סמיכה smicha and so on. Now
we continue getting back to the fifty of the case of rape
and seduction and also to an implication of its special status as
a קנס. knas. So let's take a look now as we move
into the fourth פרק. perek. נערה שנתפתתה, naara shenitpateta, a woman that
was seduced, actually now we're going into seduction and not rape. בושת
ופגם וקנסה של אביה. boshet upgam v'knasah shel aviha. So the בושת
boshet and פגם, pgam, the shame and the injury and the fine,
the fifty shekel goes to the father. And again even though she
is consensual, she's not in her own rights to be consensual about
it and therefore there still is injury and it goes to the
father. והצער v'hatza'ar and additionally the pain and suffering, בתפוסה bitfusah in
a case of rape. So here's a new word for rape, not
אנוסה anussah but תפוסה tfusah because the תורה Torah says והיא לא
נתפסה, v'hi lo nitpasah, she was not grabbed. So to be נתפסה
nitpasah to be forcibly seized is the language in the גמרא Gemara
in the תורה Torah by rape. So in a case of rape
there's also צער tza'ar and that also goes to the father. So
that's repeating the idea that all the payments go to the father.
Now we're going to look at exceptions to that case. עמדה בדין.
amda b'din. Didn't we say that there
was no צער tza'ar earlier?
Except for rape. That's what it says, והצער בתפוסה, v'hatza'ar bitfusah, and
there's צער tza'ar payment in a case of rape. עמדה בדין, amda
b'din, now let's say we have the court case. And it was
brought to the court and the בית דין Beis Din said to
the guy חייב אתה ליתן לו, chayav ata liten lo, you have
to pay the father. Now עד שלא מת אב ad shelo met
av and the father is alive at the time of the court
case. And
then they ruled that the guy has to pay. They had the
court case, the father was alive, they ruled that the guy had
to pay the father. Fine, הרי הן של אחין, harei hen shel
achin, then the father already is entitled to the money because he
was around when the ruling occurred in בית דין. Beis Din. מת
אב, met av, now let's say the father dies after the court
case. So the father already was awarded the funds. So even if
he didn't pocket it yet, הרי הן של אחין, harei hen shel
achin, then that passes on to his sons, the brothers of the
woman who was raped. Because he was entitled to that, it's like
a guy now owes him a hundred dollars, he dies so that
debt transfers to his heirs. הרי הן של אחין. harei hen shel
achin. לא הספיקה לעמוד בדין עד שמת אב. lo hispika la'amod b'din
ad shemet av. Let's say that you did not yet have the
court case and the father had died. The father died before the
rapist was taken to court. So
now הרי הן של עצמה, harei hen shel atzmah, now it's when
we have the court case she is the litigant and it is
awarded to her.
So this gets back to the idea and
meaning regardless of when she she's a בוגרת bogaret or not.
Correct. Because the basic idea is that as we've said or this
is conceptually the easiest way to explain it that the guy did
this act of injury in rape to this woman. He owes the
money to the woman but the father's entitled to it through his
daughter, that he's entitled to anything that money would go to his
daughter. If he's dead when the time of the court case comes
then she's been emancipated from the father so now she can collect
it directly. And therefore if the father's dead and they have the
court case she's the one that gets the money. הרי הן של
עצמה. harei hen shel atzmah. עמדה בדין עד שלא בגרה. amda b'din
ad shelo bagra. Now let's say
she
has the court case and she is still a קטנה. ktana. הריהן
של אב. Hareihen shel av. Then they, then they, then they go
to the father. That's again assuming that the father's alive. So this
is just going back to our case, but we're now going to
be dealing with the question of her age. So the father's alive
and she's a קטנה, ktana, then the father gets it.
Why קטנה? ktana? Maybe a נערה. nara. נערה, nara, fine.
מת אב הריהן של אחין, Meis av hareihen shel achin, then the
father dies after he's been awarded the money, it goes to the
brothers. Okay, so fine, that was basically reviewing the other case except
just pointing out that in the case that the father gets it,
not only is the father alive, but she's also not a בוגרת.
bogeres. But in the two exceptions to that, one is that the
father is dead, or exception number two, at the time of the
court case she's a בוגרת. bogeres. לא הספיקה לעמוד בדין עד שבגרה,
Lo hispika la'amod badin ad shebagra, or she's a בוגרת, bogeres, she
is now a full adult and fully emancipated at the time of
the court case, then הריהן של עצמה, hareihen shel atzmah, they're hers.
Okay? So bottom line the משנה Mishna's saying, when did the father
gets it through her, in order for him to get it, he
has to be alive and she has to be a נערה nara
or קטנה ktana at the time of the court case. If she
is emancipated, what? At the time of the ending of the case.
If she's emancipated when the case is over, when it gets awarded,
she is either the father has died or she's a בוגרת, bogeres,
then the money gets awarded to her and not to the father.
רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, now Rabbi Shimon says, אם לא
הספיקה לגבות עד שמת אב הריהן של עצמה. im lo hispika ligbos
ad shemeis av hareihen shel atzmah. No, it's not enough that actually
for the father to be awarded it, it's not enough that there's
the גמר דין. gmar din. For it to actually be considered the
father's, actually the money has to be paid out already. It has
to be in the father's pocket. But if basically even after the
court case the father before the money was paid out the father
died, then it's still going to be paid to her, not to
the father. So according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, even after גמר
דין, gmar din, the obligation is still not directly to the father,
but it's to the father through the daughter. You get it? So
the case is seen to court and the guy says, okay ראובן,
Reuven, you seduced, you know, שמעון'ס Shimon's daughter here, you raped her,
you owe שמעון Shimon a thousand dollars. But really they're not saying
you owe שמעון Shimon a thousand dollars. Really even after גמר דין,
gmar din, they're saying you owe רחל Rachel a thousand dollars and
שמעון Shimon is going to collect. Even after גמר דין, gmar din,
says רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So therefore as long as if the
father dies before he's collected even after גמר דין, gmar din, the
daughter still going to pocket it because the money always goes to
the father through the daughter even after גמר דין. gmar din. Okay?
I know. Now neither of them have a פסוק. pasuk. One minute,
let's just read the משנה, Mishna, top of מ"ב ע"א. mem-bais amud
aleph. מעשה ידיה ומציאתה, Ma'aseh yadeha u'metzi'asah, אף על פי שלא גבתה
מת אב הריהן של אחין.
af al pi
shelo gavsa meis av hareihen shel achin. However, this is different even
according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. This case about collection for personal
injury is different from her earnings. Money that she earns, she I
don't know, she goes out and she weaves a garment or she
goes out and she gets a job. Or she finds an object.
In that case even let's take the case of a job, it's
an easier example. So she's waiting to get her monthly salary and
then the father dies. It doesn't matter. Once that money was earned,
even before it's collected, then it really is automatically the father's money.
And if he dies, then it passes down הריהן של אחין hareihen
shel achin to the brothers. So that's interesting, right? He's not saying
that every time the father collects on behalf of his daughter, right,
in most cases, right, as soon as the debt is incurred, it
becomes directly a debt to the father, whereas for some reason in
the case of קנס knas according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, even
after בית דין Beis Din has ruled, it still only gets paid
through the daughter and if the father dies before it's been paid,
the daughter still collects. We'll see about why in the גמרא. Gemara.
How old is the girl in רבי שמעון'ס Rabbi Shimon's case?
Also 12 and a, you know, under 12 and a half, נערה
nara or קטנה, ktana, yes. Yeah, נערה, nara, קטנה. ktana. Right, once
she's a בוגרת bogeres it could be the same as the father
dying, right? The father dying should be assumed to be the same
הלכה halacha as her becoming a בוגרת. bogeres. Either way it's a
scenario where she becomes emancipated,
right, before the either before the end of the court case or
before the money's been collected.
But you can see in the case before that he's disagreeing with,
if he passes to the brothers, it's fine.
It's not
about passing the brothers is a funny way of thinking about it.
The brothers is only an issue about once we've said whether it's
her the father's or hers, who the father's are collecting because of
an heir. He says that if it's a קנס, knas, it always
goes through her. And therefore if the father has died when it
comes time to collect, even after the court has ruled, it's still
going to go through her and therefore she's going to collect. Brothers
don't have the rights to her the same way the father does.
So when it's when when the father's alive, essentially she gets paid
and then it transfers to the father. Once the father is dead,
she gets paid and it stops with her.
But in the case before that he's disagreeing with, if he passes
away it goes first to the brothers and then
No, according to the חכמים Chachamim the reason they say it goes
to the brothers is because of logically what the חכמים Chachamim are
saying is is that after גמר דין, gmar din, it's a debt
directly to the father. Okay, so there was a גמר דין, gmar
din, it became a debt directly to directly to the father. The
father died, so the brothers inherit from the father. He's cut out.
Okay? So whereas רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no, even after גמר
דין, gmar din, it only gets to the father through her. So
therefore even if the father has died and she hasn't collected yet
and the money hasn't been paid yet, so it goes to it
would normally have gone to her and then transferred immediately to the
father. Right? It would have been like call forwarding. Think of it
like a type of a call forwarding, okay? But there wasn't the
call forwarding, so it stopped at her. Okay. All right, now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
מאי, Mai, top of מב Mem-Beit עמוד א. Amud-Aleph. מאי קמשמע לן?
Mai kamashmalan? No talking guys, we're behind. מאי קמשמע לן? Mai kamashmalan?
What is our משנה Mishnah teaching us? Now of course a thing
should be teaching us a lot, but let's see what the גמרא
Gemara is going to ask. Well, not not the whole thing about
who dies when and when and whatever, okay? תנינא, Tanina, we already
taught in an earlier משנה: Mishnah: המפתה נותן שלושה דברים והאונס ארבעה.
hamfateh notain shlosha dvarim ve'ones arba.
So the first part of the משנה Mishnah we already knew, that
the seducer pays three payments and the rapist four. So the גמרא
Gemara says: המפתה נותן בושת ופגם וקנס, hamfateh notain boshet u-pgam u-knas,
the seducer pays the, you know, embarrassment, injury and the fine. מוסיף
עליו האונס שנותן את הצער mosif alav ha-ones she-notain et ha-tzaar and
the rapist adds to it that he gives the pain suffering. לאביה
איצטריכא ליה. la-aviha itzterech lei. No, so the גמרא Gemara says: לאביה
איצטריכא ליה. la-aviha itzterech lei. No, no, the חדוש chidush here was
that it all goes to the father. The גמרא Gemara says: לאביה
נמי פשיטא. la-aviha nami peshita. That's also פשיטא. peshita. מדיהיב מפתה. mide'kayahiv
mefateh. And how do we know it's obvious? Because and now here's
a point that we've been saying implicitly before, here it says explicitly.
מדיהיב מפתה, mide'kayahiv mefateh,
the fact that the seducer still has to pay even though she
did it all consensually, so that shows that it's the father who's
being paid because the, right, if it was she that was being
paid, then why would you pay her? She was she agreed to
it. So דאילו לעצמה, de'ilei atzma, because if the payment goes to
her, אמאי יהיב מפתה? amai yahiv mefateh? Why did the why why
would the seducer pay? מדעתה עבד. midaatah avad. He did it based
on her own acquiescence, okay?
So the גמרא Gemara says, מדעתה עבד. midaatah avad.
So the גמרא Gemara says fine, אמר בדין איצטריכא ליה, amar be'din
itzterech lei, פלוגתא דרבי שמעון ורבנן. plugta de'Rabbi Shimon ve-Rabbanan. So, so
no,
so the whole חדוש chidush here is what happens after the court
case. Right? Has the father died before after the court case? Has
she become a בוגרת bogeres before after the court case? The debate
of the רבנן Rabbanan and רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that's what this
is all about. That's the other stuff was just a lead-in lead-in
to that. Okay fine. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay fine. Let me just one sec, hold on, I just want
to think about something one second. Yes fine.
Okay,
so גמרא Gemara says like this. תנן, Tnan, תנן התם. tnan hatam.
We taught over there. אנסת ופיתית את בתי. onasta u-pitet bitti. This
guy says you raped or seduced my daughter. Now this is a
משנה Mishnah in שבועות. Shvuot. Now in שבועות Shvuot the following there's
a הלכה halacha about a קרבן korban when you are of of
כפירת ממון. kfiras mamon. If a person takes a vow that somebody
that somebody says you know this is actually just weeks coming פרשה,
parsha, somebody says: וכחש בעמיתו בפקדון או בתשומת יד או בגזל או
עשק את עמיתו. v-khichesh ba-amito be-pikadon o vi-tsumet yad o ve-gazel o
ashaq et amito. Right?
So basically somebody says where's that money that I gave you for
safekeeping and the person takes and says I don't know what you're
talking about. He says swear to me. So he takes an oath
and he's lying. So he's using God's name and using an oath
as a way of stealing. So besides the sin of stealing, it's
also involving God in that process and therefore the punishment is that
he pays the principal plus a fifth and he brings a special
קרבן. korban. Okay, so now in order to do all of that
it has to be a time it has to be a circumstance
in which taking the oath is denying something that were I to
admit it I would have to pay. And there here's another place
where it matters whether something is קנס knas or ממון. mamon. Because
if something is ממון mamon then that's a type of an oath
I'm חייב chayav for because were I to admit it I'd have
to pay. Whereas if it's קנס, knas, if you tell me you
stole from me and therefore you pay let's say the principal I'm
here to collect the כפל, kefel, but double payment and you say
no no no I've already paid that up I don't know what
you're talking about, then I'm actually not חייב chayav for taking a
false oath because even if I were to admit that I owe
you the כפל, kefel, that admission doesn't obligate me. Right? That's the
principle again, מודה בקנס פטור. modeh bi-knas patur. Right exactly. There you
go. Okay so now here's the debate, so here's the משנה. Mishnah.
Okay. אנסת ופיתית את בתי. onasta u-pitet bitti. This guy says you
raped or seduced my daughter. והוא אומר לא אנסתי ולא פיתיתי, ve-hu
omer lo onasti ve-lo piteti, I did not do it you're making
it up. משביעך אני, mashpi'acha ani, swear to me. ואמר אמן, ve-amar
amen, yes, and he said אמן amen he accepted the שבועה. shvua.
ואחר כך הודה, ve-achar hodeh, and then he admitted that he had
raped or seduced the daughter. Okay, so is he being demanded ממון
mamon or קנס knas here? So חייב, chayav, so he has to
pay. רבי שמעון פוטר, Rabbi Shimon poter, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon exempts.
שאינו משלם קנס על פי עצמו, she'eino m'shalem knas al pi atzmo,
because you would not pay even were you to admit that the
guy were to admit that he raped or seduced you would not
pay קנס. knas. So therefore he does not pay by denial since
there would be no payment by admission. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמרו לו, amru lo, they said to him, אף על פי שאינו
משלם קנס על פי עצמו, af al pi she'eino m'shalem knas al
pi atzmo, it's true, for the קנס knas you're not going to
have to pay by your own admission but. משלם בושת ופגם על
פי עצמו, meshalem boshet upegam al pi atzmo, but you would pay
for the embarrassment and the injury.
That line is in the משנה? mishna?
Yes, that is part of this משנה. mishna. So it becomes a
very almost not really so much of a consequential debate because they
don't really seem as the גמרא Gemara is going to be saying
later on to be debating any of the legal points. They both
agree that you're not חייב chayav for making a false oath about
a קנס. knas. You're only חייב chayav for making a false oath
about ממון. mamon. The only question is that when somebody says, you
raped my daughter, is he implicitly demanding the payment for the קנס
knas and therefore a denial would not obligate the person? Or is
he implicitly demanding the payment for the בושת boshet and פגם pegam
and therefore a denial would obligate the person? And why don't I
know why we don't say he's implicitly demanding both? So the guy's
at least חייב chayav for the שבועה shvua for the half of
it that relates to the בושת boshet and פגם. pegam. Anyway, that's
their debate. When the guy says, everybody agrees you don't pay for
קנס, knas, you do pay for ממון, mamon, and similarly there's no
קרבן korban for קנס, knas, there's only a קרבן korban for ממון.
mamon. And the question is which one is he really demanding? Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
That's the ברייתא. braita. So now the גמרא Gemara says the following.
And notice by the way it's רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So we're
going to... but nobody in principle is disagreeing which tells us, so
the גמרא Gemara now is going to hone in on רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon even though there's no real reason to say there's a
principal debate between רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the רבנן. rabanan. So
let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says. בעי מיניה
אביי מרבה. Ba'ei minei Abaye me-Rabbah. אביי Abaye asked from רבה Rabbah
the following question. האומר לחברו, Ha-omer lachaveiro, somebody says to his fellow:
אנסת ופתית את בתי, Anasta ufitita et biti, you raped or seduced
my daughter, ועמדתיך בדין, ve-amadeticha badin,
and not only did you do that act, we actually brought the
case to court, ונתחייבת לי ממון, venitchayavta li mamon, and the court
ruled that you owed me the money. והוא אומר vehu omer לא
אנסתי ולא פתיתי ולא עמדתני
בדין, lo anasti velo pititi velo amadetani badin, no it's all a
lie, I never did it and I never certainly was taken to
court, ולא נתחייבתי לך ממון, velo nitchayavti lecha mamon, and I never
was obligated, ונשבע והודה, venishba vehoda,
and he swore and then he admitted that he had lied. לרבי
שמעון מה? Le-Rabbi Shimon mah? What's the story according to רבי שמעון?
Rabbi Shimon? All right, exactly. כיון דעמד בדין ממון הוי. keivan de-amad
badin mamon havei.
Do we say once there was a court case, then the קנס
knas converts to a case of ממון? mamon? Okay, when we say
if I admit to a קנס, knas, right, I don't get, I'm
not obligated, right? So let's say I say for example, my ox
gored your slave. Okay, I'm not obligated because I'm admitting to a
קנס knas and as we said a קנס knas is something that
needs to be imposed by בית דין. Beis Din. It won't, I
won't be able to obligate myself to it based on my own
admission. But let's say I say, my ox gored your slave and
בית דין Beis Din obligated me to pay. Am I now admitting
to a קנס knas or am I now admitting to ממון? mamon?
Right, I'm actually saying that the fine had already been imposed by
בית דין. Beis Din.
So it's still, okay, it starts
in a קנס, knas, but now I'm admitting to a debt that
is imposed by בית דין, Beis Din, right? It's part of the
reason my admission can't obligate me is because there's no debt without
בית דין Beis Din imposing it. Now I'm admitting to the fact
that בית דין Beis Din had imposed the debt. So I'm admitting
to a debt imposed by בית דין. Beis Din. Who cares what
it originated in? Does the חיוב chiyuv of בית דין Beis Din
convert a קנס knas to ממון? mamon? That's generally the assumption, that
if I admit that I was obligated in a court, I can
obligate myself because then I don't need בית דין Beis Din to
impose it based on my own admission, it's already been imposed and
I'm just admitting to a debt that's been imposed by בית דין.
Beis Din. So therefore that's the גמרא's Gemara question. Is that true?
If what is being demanded and denied, claimed and denied, is not
the קנס knas itself but the קנס knas imposed by בית דין,
Beis Din, would that already be considered ממון mamon and therefore you
would be חייב chayav a קרבן שבועה korban shvua since you were,
and
the related question is would you be חייב chayav based on just
admitting to that type of a debt?
As opposed to what?
As opposed to saying it still has the aspect, it still has
the character of קנס. knas.
No, maybe it's time I go and pay you then. This is
already outside of בית דין. Beis Din. I'm going and saying, well
you know, I was already חייב chayav in בית דין Beis Din
and here's your,
I don't understand what
you're talking about.
קנס knas starts with something that I'm not obligated for based on
my own admission. The question is does the nature of קנס knas
become converted to ממון mamon once בית דין Beis Din has created
the obligation? And therefore if I admit to an obligation of a
קנס knas imposed by בית דין, Beis Din, am I admitting to
ממון? mamon?
No, but maybe by the time by the time I already come
to pay you, it's not done in the בית דין Beis Din
at the same day, I'm already coming saying
I'll pay you
from whatever בית דין...
Beis Din... What? What? I come to you and I say, Michael,
your ox gored my slave
and I want to bring you to court and I want to
bring... and I want to sort of get you to pay. I
don't understand what you're what you're asking. At that stage it's only
a קנס knas and your own admission won't obligate you. If I
say a year ago this happened and בית דין Beis Din imposed
a debt, then I'm saying you owe me the money. I don't
need to bring you to בית דין Beis Din to prove that
your ox gored my slave, we did that a year ago.
Right right, I'm saying but at any time by the time like
you know I come around and I pay you, like you know
if I... with your daughter whatever it is.
Fine, yes exactly, at that time it is ממון. mamon. Correct, fine.
All right. Anyway so that's the גמרא's Gemara question.
Okay so לרבי שמעון מה? Le-Rabbi Shimon mah? What would we say?
The תוספות Tosafot says why are you only asking according to רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon is not clear because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and
the רבנן rabanan don't disagree in principle, but okay, כיון דעמד בדין
ממון הוי. keivan de-amad badin mamon havei. Once there was a court
case, it now actually exists as ממון. mamon. And since we're since
we're debating whether or not the court case existed, you know, in
the past, what we're really debating is a ממון mamon obligation. And
therefore I would bring a קרבן שבועה. korban shvua. ומחייב ליה קרבן
שבועה u-mechayve lei korban shvua and I would bring a קרבן שבועה,
korban shvua, similarly to a similar question תוספות Tosafot explicitly even has
this in the גירסא girsa of the גמרא, Gemara, that if you're
telling that I would obligate myself based on my own admission and
therefore there would be a קרבן שבועה korban shvua because we're debating
whether or not the court has already found me guilty in the
past. או דילמא o dilma or do we say אף על גב
דעמד בדין, af al gav de-amad ba-din, even though there's already been
a court case, קנס הוי, knas havei, it still retains its identity
as a קנס knas since it started by קנס knas it retains
its identity and תוספות Tosafot by the way there's a debate רש"י
תוספות Rashi Tosafot here but I'll just say in תוספות Tosafot says
that therefore even were I to admit it, even were I to
come and say I admit that last year I was found guilty
in a בית דין beis din for my ox goring your slave,
I don't have to pay you because it's something that starts as
קנס, knas, it always retains the character of קנס knas and I
can never be obligated based on my own admission. And in the
same way I won't be obligated based on my own admission, I
won't be obligated if I take a שבועה. shvua. Okay, so here
the גמרא'ס Gemara's asking a core question about when קנס knas changes
its identity to ממון. mamon. Is it after the court case? And
then once which is logical because now it just exists as a
fine imposed by court. Who cares what the past history of it
is, right? I mean if a court went ahead and said that
I owed somebody a thousand dollars or whatever, now it's just a
debt. The past history is irrelevant. Okay, or do we say it
still retains its identity as קנס knas and the נפקא מינא nafka
mina is when I admit to it, do I have to pay?
And similarly therefore when I deny it, is there going to be
a קרבן שבועה? korban shvua? That's the question.
So that's what אביי Abaye asked רבא. Rava. אמר ליה, amar lei,
רבא Rava said back to him, ממונא הוא מחייב ליה קרבן שבועה,
mamona hu mechayve lei korban shvua, it is ממון mamon at that
stage and therefore if you deny if you admit to it you're
חייב chayav and if you deny it you're going to bring a
קרבן. korban. Okay. איתיבי, esvei, now let me ask on this. רבי
שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, we have a ברייתא braisa about this
קרבן שבועה. korban shvua. רבי שמעון אומר יכול האומר לחברו, Rabbi Shimon
omer yachol ha-omer le-chavero, I would think if somebody said to his
friend, אנסת ופתית את בתי, anasata u-pityata et biti, that you have
raped or seduced my daughter, והוא אמר לא אנסתי ולא פתיתי, ve-hu
omer lo anasti ve-lo pityati, it did not never happened. Or he
says המית שורך את עבדי, hemit shorcha et avdi, your ox gored
my slave, killed my slave, thank you. והוא אמר לא המית, ve-hu
omer lo hemit, it did not happen. או שמא לו עבדו, o
shema lo avdo,
or his slave said to him, הפלת את שיני, hippalta et shini,
you knocked out my tooth and then the slave goes free and
that interestingly considered to be a type of a קנס, knas, I
don't know because maybe because it's disproportionate to the cost of the
tooth, right? So therefore that's considered to be a type of a
קנס. knas. וסימאת את עיני, ve-simata et eini, or you blinded my
eye. והוא אמר לא הפלתי ולא סימאתי, ve-hu omer lo hippalti ve-lo
simati, I did not do it. Okay, so therefore he's being demanded
a קנס knas and he denies it. ונשבע והודה, ve-nishba ve-hoda, and
he swore falsely and then he admitted. יכול יהא חייב, yachol yehei
chayav, maybe you'd be חייב, chayav, right? The interesting thing by the
way is that a slave is bringing his master to court and
that's considered totally acceptable, right? The only question here is whether it's
a קנס knas or not. Maybe you'd be חייב chayav this קרבן.
korban. תלמוד לומר וכחש בעמיתו בפקדון או בתשומת יד או בגזל או
עשק את עמיתו, Talmud lomar ve-khichesh ba-amito be-pikadon o be-tesumet yad o
be-gazel o ashak et amito, you deny your friend regarding regarding a
surety, not surety, what's a פקדון, pikadon, a
not collateral, פקדון pikadon is just an object for safe keeping. Anyway,
or anyway, you know, or some type of other type of of
abuse or stealing etc. או מצא אבידה וכחש בה, o matza aveida
ve-khichesh ba, or you found a lost object and you denied that
you had his lost object in your house. ונשבע על שקר ve-nishba
al shaker and you swore falsely, swore falsely, then you bring this
קרבן. korban. מה אלו מיוחדים שהן ממון, ma elu meyuchadim she-hein mamon,
those things are all monetary obligations. אף כל שהן ממון, af kol
she-hein mamon, so similarly you'd only be חייב chayav by something that's
a ממון mamon obligation. יצאו אלו שהן קנס, yatzu elu she-hein knas,
you're not חייב chayav when you swear falsely on something which is
only a קנס. knas. Okay, that's רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Now what
does that prove? Our question was what's the story after גמר דין?
gemar din? So that doesn't isn't clear whether it's before after גמר
דין, gemar din, so that's what the גמרא Gemara now comes to
argue. מאי לאו, mai lav, are we not talking about בשעמד בדין,
be-she-amad ba-din, are we not talking about since we use the פסוק
pasuk to prove it, right? Here's like a way of understanding it.
If really you would not be obligated when you admitted to it,
you wouldn't really need a פסוק. pasuk. If you would concede you
wouldn't be obligated, how could you be found liable for lying and
denying since you wouldn't even be obligated if you conceded? So maybe
the assumption is since we're using a פסוק pasuk to prove it,
maybe the point that we're proving is that even if it originated
as קנס, knas, even if it's after גמר דין, gemar din, it
still is going to be something you're going to be exempt of.
מאי לאו, mai lav, are we not talking about בשעמד בדין, be-she-amad
ba-din, that even after even if what we're debating is an obligation
based on something in the past that there already was a court
case about, that even there you'll be exempt because it started as
a קנס? knas? Is that not the case?
It'll always retain its identity for a קנס. knas. אמר ליה לא
בשלא עמד בדין. amar lei lo be-she-lo amad ba-din. No, we're talking
about before עמד בדין, amad ba-din, that's a straightforward קנס knas and
that's why you're exempt, but maybe it would change its identity afterwards.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute. והא מדרישא בשעמד בדין *v'ha
mide'reisha be'she'amad b'din* סיפא נמי בשעמד בדין *seifa nami be'she'amad b'din*. One
minute, the beginning of that ברייתא *braita* is talking about that there
was a court case, so the end of it must also be
that there's a court case. What was the beginning? דתני רישא *d'tani
reisha*. We taught in the beginning of the ברייתא *braita* and this
is now a position of the חכמים *Chachamim*, not רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon*. אין לי אלא דברים שמשלמין עליהם את הקרן *ein
li ella devarim she'meshalmin aleihem et ha'keren*. I only know that you
bring a קרבן שבועה korban shvua, *korban shevuah* things that you'd pay
the principal. תשלומי כפל ותשלומי ארבעה וחמישה ואונס ומפתה ומוציא שם רע
מנין *tashlumei kefel v'tashlumei arba'ah v'chamishah v'ones u'mefateh u'motzi shem ra minayin*?
How do I know that you even do a קרבן שבועה korban
shvua, *korban shevuah* on things like payment of double and four and
five and various cases of burglary or cases of seduction and rape
and libel? All these are קנסות *kenasot*. How do I know even
there you bring a קרבן שבועה korban shvua, *korban shevuah*? תלמוד לומר
ומעלה מעל ריבה *talmud lomar u'ma'alah ma'al ribah*. And you did a
trespass. So that double language is to tell me even in cases
of קנס knas. *kenas*. So basically what's confusing about this is that
we've got the רישא *reisha* and the סיפא *seifa*. And the רישא
*reisha* is the רבנן *Rabbanan* and the סיפא *seifa* is רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon*. So the רישא *reisha* says how do I
know that אונס ומפתה ones u-mifateh *ones u'mefateh*, I mean it has
other cases as well but we'll just focus on אונס ומפתה ones
u-mifateh *ones u'mefateh*. How do you know that you bring a קרבן
שבועה korban shvua *korban shevuah*, קרבן שבועה korban shvua *korban shevuah*? How
do we know you're חייב chayav? *chayav*? Because it says ומעלה מעל
*u'ma'alah ma'al*. And then it says רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*
says right אונס ומפתה ones u-mifateh
*ones u'mefateh* you're going to be פטור patur *patur* because it says
וכיחש וכיחש *v'kichash v'kichash* right או בגזל או באבדה *o b'gezel o
b'avedah*
etc. blah blah blah blah blah. Which is basically ממון mamon *mamon*
and not קנס knas *kenas*. So here you have the ברייתא *braita*.
First it says אונס ומפתה ones u-mifateh *ones u'mefateh* you're חייב chayav
*chayav* and then רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon* says אונס ומפתה
ones u-mifateh *ones u'mefateh* you're פטור patur *patur*. Okay, so this is
understood to be the חכמים *Chachamim*, okay, although they weren't said. So
it's a debate whether you're חייב chayav *chayav* or not by אונס
ומפתה Oness u'mefateh, *ones u'mefateh*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says there
is no way the חכמים *Chachamim* would say that you're going to
be חייב chayav, *chayav* if it was not עמד בדין amad b'din
*amad b'din*. It is impossible to conceive of the possibility, it is
impossible to conceive that you could be חייב *chayav* for denying something
that were you to have admitted it you'd also be exempt. So
when the חכמים *Chachamim* are saying you're חייב *chayav* for אונס ומפתה
*ones u'mefateh*, they must be talking about עמד בדין amad b'din *amad
b'din*.
דקנסא מיחייב עמד בדין amad b'din. נו *d'kenasa michuyav amad b'din, no*?
Well yeah but you could admit to the act before the עמד
בדין amad b'din. *amad b'din*. Okay? But if you're going to be
חייב *chayav* for denying a case of קנס knas, *kenas*, it would
only be some type of a קנס knas *kenas* that had you
admitted to it you would have been חייב *chayav* for. Okay? So
therefore if the חכמים *Chachamim* say you're חייב *chayav* for admitting to
a קנס knas, *kenas*, for denying a קנס knas, *kenas*, it must
have been a case of עמד בדין amad b'din. *amad b'din*. And
therefore when רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon* says you're פטור patur.
*patur*, it's also got to be a case of עמד בדין amad
b'din *amad b'din*. So you see רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon*
exempts you even in a case of
עמד בדין amad b'din *amad b'din*. Okay, so that's a
pretty good example, pretty good proof that רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon. *Rabbi
Shimon's* approach applies even after עמד בדין amad b'din *amad b'din*. Okay,
so אמר ליה *amar lei*, so רבא Rava *Rava* said back to
אביי Abaye *Abaye*, יכילנא לשנויי לך *yachilna l'shanuyei lach*. I could answer
you. רישא בשעמד בדין וסיפא בשלא עמד בדין amad b'din, וכולה רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon היא *reisha be'she'amad b'din v'seifa be'shelo amad b'din v'chulah
Rabbi Shimon hi*. I could say to you that actually no, here
where it says you're חייב *chayav*, okay, here where it says you're
חייב *chayav* is because it was עמד בדין amad b'din *amad b'din*.
Here where it says you're פטור *patur* is when it was לא
עמד בדין amad b'din *lo amad b'din*. And there's really no debate
of חכמים *Chachamim* and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon*. Actually it's
all
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon*. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*
is saying אונס ומפתה *ones u'mefateh* you're חייב *chayav* if it was
after עמד בדין amad b'din *amad b'din* and it became ממון mamon?
*mamon* and therefore if you admit you'd be חייב *chayav* so if
you deny you're חייב *chayav*. And however אונס ומפתה *ones u'mefateh* you're
פטור *patur* if it was before עמד בדין amad b'din *amad b'din*.
Okay? So I could say that it's all, that the חייב *chayav*
is after and the פטור *patur* is before and it's all רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*. But he says ושנויא דחיקא לא משנינא
לך *u'shinuya d'chika lo m'shanina lach*. I'm not going to give you
a bad answer. דאם כן *de'im ken*, because if I would have
claimed that, אמרת לי *amarta li*, you'd say back to me, ליתני
רישא רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon Omer: *litni reisha Rabbi Shimon omer*.
That רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon's* name should have appeared at
the beginning. או ליתני סיפא דברי רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *o litni
seifa divrei Rabbi Shimon*. Or it should appear at the very end.
The fact that here you say, here it says
אונס ומפתה *ones u'mefateh* you're
חייב *chayav*, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* says אונס ומפתה *ones
u'mefateh* you're פטור *patur*. So we see clearly that רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says פטור even after
עמידה בדין. amada b'din. So, so you're right. According to רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon you remain פטור even after עמידה בדין, amada b'din, it
retains its character of קנס. knas ומודינא לך, u'modina lach, but I
will concede to you לענין קרבן שבועה l'inyan korban shvua דרחמנא פטריה.
d'Rachmana patrei. When it comes to the case of the קרבן שבועה,
korban shvua. there we have a special פסוק. pasuk. There I agree,
my argument would be that according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon after
עמידה בדין amada b'din it becomes ממון mamon in other areas. Okay?
But when it comes to the קרבן שבועה, korban shvua, there you're
right. There רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that remains the identity of
a קנס knas and you remain off the hook. Okay? Because the
תורה Torah exempted him מכחש. mi-v'kichesh. The פסוק pasuk of וכחש בעמיתו,
v'kichesh ba'amito, etc., is to tell you that by קרבן שבועה, korban
shvua, if it started as קנס, knas you're off the hook. So
now again, this is confusing. To remind you what we said.
The question אביי asked רבה Raba is: after עמידה בדין amada b'din
according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon? does קנס knas. convert to ממון?
mamon, And his answer was yes. Actually, he said yes for קרבן
שבועה korban shvua, it does. But now he's taking back the קרבן
שבועה korban shvua. part of the claim. Because now we've proven that
for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, even after עמידה בדין, amada b'din, it
retains its character for קנס, knas you're still off the hook for
קרבן שבועה. korban shvua So he says, fine. For רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon when it comes to קרבן שבועה, korban shvua. there's a special
פסוק. pasuk. Even after עמידה בדין, amada b'din, מכחש, mi-v'kichesh, even after
עמידה בדין, amada b'din, it still has its character of קנס, knas.
you're still off the hook. But what I meant to say was
that it will convert to ממון mamon. for all other purposes. But
for קרבן שבועה, korban shvuah, you'll be off the hook according to
רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon קנס knas, becomes ממון, mamon. but the קרבן korban remains
as a קנס knas and he's פטור.
Well, that's a funny way of saying it. In the laws of
קרבן שבועה, korban shvuah if there's a special requirement that it starts
its life as ממון. mamon, Something that started its life as קנס
knas is technically exempt from the קרבן שבועה. korban shvuah But in
other areas of הלכה, halacha, in general, if I had: what is
the identity of this thing now that it's עמידה בדין? amada b'din?
Its identity is ממון. mamon But even though right now it's ממון,
mamon. you're off the hook for קרבן שבועה korban shvuah because it
started its life as קנס.
knas From קנס knas to ממון mamon. already?
Well, first of all, if he admits to it, are you חייב?
Right? So there's a whole מחלוקת רש"י ותוספות machlokes Rashi u'Tosafos at
this stage what we think the story would be according to רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon if you would admit to it. But, you know,
then the other issue about the father dying and it transferring to
the sons and all those issues, okay? So basically he's saying, look,
my claim still is that according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon after
עמידה בדין amada b'din it converts to ממון. mamon? You have proven
to me that according to רבי שמעון, you're off the hook for
a קרבן. korban. Fine, that's a special הלכה halacha in קרבן. korban.
It has to start its life not as a קנס. knas If
it started its life as a קנס, knas you're off the hook.
That's for the קרבן. korban. But basically, in all other הלכות, halachos,
this thing is considered to be ממון. mamon Okay, so now the
גמרא says like this:
וכי קאמינא ממון, v'chi ka'amina mamon, so for what הלכה halacha do
I say it's ממון? mamon להורישו לבניו, l'horisho l'vanav, to bequeath it
to your children. Now we would say the easiest thing to say
ממון mamon. is if whether if you admitted are you חייב or
not. There there's a debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos what
the הלכה halacha would be there. But his case of להורישו לבניו
l'horisho l'vanav is going to turn us to our משנה, Mishnah, which
means that in it's a general point, like if somebody dies, right,
you know, people owe this guy a million dollars, those debts transfer
to the sons, right, because it's part of the estate. But a
קנס knas. is not that way. Because a קנס knas. is not
yet a debt. So a קנס knas. does not transfer with the
estate, doesn't get bequeathed to the children, if it only existed as
a קנס knas at the time that the guy died. So here's
the question: after עמידה בדין amada b'din the guy died, then he
would say, then רבי שמעון would say it's ממון mamon. and it
would be bequeathed to the children. And also רש"י Rashi would say
also, by the way, the more simpler example, also if you admitted
to the debt you'd be חייב because it's already ממון. mamon So
after עמידה בדין amada b'din it would be considered ממון. mamon It
would transfer to the children if the guy died, if you admitted
you'd be חייב, it's only an exemption from the laws of the
קרבן שבועה. korban shvuah, Okay, so that's what now רבה Raba is
claiming. So now the גמרא says like this: איתיבי, aisei, so we're
not done with רבה Raba yet because now we're going to show
a contradiction to this, which is our משנה. Mishnah. Now we finally
tie back into our משנה. Mishnah. איתיבי, aisei, רבי שמעון אומר: Rabbi
Shimon omer אם לא הספיקה לגבות עד שמת האב, im lo hispika
l'igbos ad she'meisa av, the money wasn't collected that was owed to
this daughter before the father died. Now remember what we just said.
There was a גמר דין gmar din and then the father's going
to die. So we are now claiming that רבי שמעון admits that
when it's a גמר דין, gmar din, it gets converted to ממון
mamon and it becomes a debt to the father, and if the
father dies, it gets bequeathed to the estate, right? That's what we
said. That it does get converted to ממון mamon for רבי שמעון
in the משנה. Mishnah. רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon omer says that
no, that until the money's paid out it'll still go to the
girl. It doesn't become a debt to the father that gets bequeathed
to the estate.
Right.
Okay.
רבי שמעון אומר אם לא הספיק לגבות im lo hispik ligdos if
she didn't collect the money עד שמת אב ad she-met av until
the father died הרי הן של עצמה harei hen shel atzma she
keeps it. So just the fact that there's עמד בדין amad badin.
does not make it ממון mamon. to the father and to get
bequeathed to the estate. ואי אמרת ממון הוה לירותיה לבנא v'im amarta
mamon hava lirishei l'bana and if after עמד בדין amad badin, it
becomes a monetary debt that he bequeaths to the children, so לעצמה
אמאי? l'atzma amai? Why does she keep it? דאחין בעו למהוי d'achin
ba'ei l'hava should go to the brothers, to the father's sons. It's
a ירושה. yerusha. So why does רבי שמעון disagree with the משנה?
Mishnah? So that seems to be that רבי שמעון in general considers
something to remain a קנס knas. even after עמד בדין. So אמר
רבא amar Rava so רבא says האי מילתא קשיא בה לרבה ורב
יוסף עשרין ותרתין שנין. hai milsa kashya ba Rabba v'Rav Yosef esrin
v'tarten shanin. רבה Rabba and רב יוסף Rav Yosef were challenged by
this issue for 22 years. Now תוספות Tosafos points out why did
you have to worry about it? Why not just retract your statement?
Right? All of the evidence points to the idea that for רבי
שמעון it remains a קנס knas until the very end, even after
עמד בדין. So why are you having such a hard time? Oh,
I can't fit this into the משנה, Mishnah, just change your opinion!
Say look, רבי שמעון says it remains a קנס. knas, So תוספות
Tosafos says it's clear that they had a tradition that even according
to רבי שמעון it got converted to ממון mamon. after עמד בדין.
But now he's got a problem. In the case of קרבן שבועה,
korban shvuah, it's clear that it's still a קנס. knas It's clear
that after עמד בדין you're still off the hook. In the case
of להורישה לבנא l'horisha l'bana in our משנה, Mishnah, it's clear that
even after עמד בדין it does not go to the sons. It
remains a קנס. knas. So רבה Rabba and רב יוסף Rav Yosef
couldn't figure out how to explain their tradition that according to רבי
שמעון it got converted to ממון. mamon. Because we see for קרבן
שבועה korban shvuah it's considered a קנס knas and we see for
bequeathing to the kids it's not considered ממון. mamon So they couldn't
understand it for 22 years. ולא איפריק v'lo ifrik and it was
not answered,
and I believe we're a little behind,
עד דיתיב רב יוסף ברישא. ad dyasiv Rav Yosef b'reisha. Now רבה
Rabba was the head of the ישיבה Yeshiva for 22 years. At
the, you know, there's a whole debate who should be the head
of the ישיבה, Yeshiva, רבה Rabba or רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. Because
רבה Rabba was the bigger תלמיד חכם talmid chacham but רב יוסף
Rav Yosef was the bigger בקי. baki. So basically רבה Rabba was
the head of the ישיבה Yeshiva and then 22 years, after 22
years he died, then רב יוסף Rav Yosef became the head of
the ישיבה. Yeshiva. So רש"י Rashi says a very beautiful thing that
even though רב יוסף Rav Yosef was more of the בקי baki
and רבה Rabba was more of like the sharp analytical תלמיד חכם,
talmid chacham, דוקא davka in order like to give status to רב
יוסף, Rav Yosef, he was assisted מן השמים min hashamayim that he
answered a question that רבה Rabba couldn't answer. So at the end
of the 22 years he now became the ראש ישיבה rosh yeshiva
and he was able to figure out the answer. Okay? So, so
עד דיתיב רב יוסף ברישא, ad dyasiv Rav Yosef b'reisha, רב יוסף
Rav Yosef became the ראש ישיבה rosh yeshiva ופרק u-prak and he
answered it. שאני התם דאמר קרא, shani hasam d'amar kra, you know
what? The case of אונס ומפתה is also an exception to the
rule. 'Cause there's a lot of exceptions. 'Cause the פסוק pasuk says
ונתן האיש השכב עמה לאבי הנערה חמשים כסף. v'natan ha-ish ha-shochev imah
l'avi ha-na'arah chamishim kasef. He should give to the father fifty כסף.
kasef. So it says the money shall already be given. לא זיכתה
תורה לאב אלא משעת נתינה. lo zichsa Torah l'av ella mishat netinah.
The father doesn't have any rights to it until it's given, it's
always fundamentally owed to the daughter. Okay? So you're right, you know
what? In general it would be ממון. mamon In this case, though,
it's still קנס. knas. Or if you want to say it in
a different way, in this case it's still being paid through the
daughter and it's not direct to the father. וכי קאמר רבא ממון
הוה לירותיה לבנא v'chi ka'amar Rava mamon hava lirishei l'bana and
when did רבה Rabba עליו השלום alav ha-shalom who's now passed away,
when did he say that it's ממון mamon. after עמד בדין according
to רבי שמעון? בשאר קנסות bi-shear knasos in other fines. So now
we have two exceptions. Even according to רבי שמעון, קנס transfers to
ממון mamon when it's עמד בדין, except number one in a קרבן
שבועה korban shvuah. we got a פסוק pasuk that says you're off
the hook. Okay? Because it started as קנס, and number two by
אונס ומפתה even after עמד בדין it's still being paid through the
daughter. So if the father dies the daughter's gonna get it. It's
not direct ממון. mamon. What?
And they wanted to pay a קרבן שבועה Korban Shevuah on that,
right.
Okay, so the,
but for something that's not אונס ומפתה and not a קרבן שבועה,
in other cases after עמד בדין it gets converted. Let's just read
one, one more line. אלא מעתה ella mei'atah if that's true, גבי
עבד gabei eved דכתיב d'chsiv כסף שלשים שקלים יתן לאדוניו, kasef shloshim
shekalim yitein l'adonav,
so it also says give straight to the master. הכא נמי לא
זיכתה תורה לאדון אלא משעת נתינה? hacha nami lo zichsa Torah l'adon
ella mishat netinah? Maybe also it's not considered his and it's not
a monetary debt until the money's actually paid out? But it says
no, יתן לחוד ונתן לחוד. yitein lachud v'nasan lachud. There's a difference
between יתן yitein which means you'll still give it, even let's say
after the guy dies you'll give it to the sons, ונתן v'nasan
means it's already been given. So in the case by the אונס
ומפתה it's only considered to be ממון mamon once it's already been
given. Okay, so one more time what we're saying is רבי שמעון
basically if you really look at it, you look at רבי שמעון
in the משנה Mishnah and you look at רבי שמעון by the
קרבן שבועה, it seems like רבי שמעון says קנס always remains a
קנס. But comes along רבה Rabba with a tradition and says no,
after עמד בדין it gets converted to ממון. But we have to
now make exceptions. קרבן שבועה is an exception, there it remains a
קנס and therefore you're not gonna give a קרבן שבועה. אונס ומפתה
is an exception and even after עמד בדין it's still being paid
through the daughter. It remains, it remains not directly to the father,
but it goes through the daughter, and if the father dies, the
daughter's going to get it even after עמד בדין. But for other
areas, not קרבן שבועה and not אונס ומפתה, there after עמד בדין,
it's going to be considered a ממון and no longer a קנס.
All right.